yes okay wonderful this is so nice I'm
I've really been looking forward to
having this conversation with you for a
while Stu it um so I don't know if
you've seen any of the other interviews
that I've done like reading pamela mang
and Riesman and uploaded was John
Fullerton um just just couple of days
ago I really enjoy because so much of
working regenerative lease also paying
attention to one's own inner story and
how we react to how we interact with the
world out there and and how we challenge
ourselves in our own frames and develop
our own cosmovision as we move along and
I know that you've I mean I've been
inspired by your work for a very long
time like when we met here on me okay I
mentioned you mentioned this to you that
you work with sim from the rim in this
little book ecological design has been
giving me some of the key pieces that
I've been building a theoretical
framework for the last 20 years and and
so you the scale linking design bit in
particular but I would love to for you
to just start with telling a little bit
your story because I know that that
you've had this amazing opportunity to
not just work with with elders like sim
but also you spend all this time with
Christopher Alexander and now you get to
work closely with John Fullerton and so
yeah how did you get to where you are
now Oh Thank You Daniel very gracious
introduction
I grew up on Vancouver Island which is a
magnificent part of the coastal
temperate rainforest that stretches all
the way from Northern California all the
way up to Alaska and my island was in
the midst of this bio cultural diversity
there's just extraordinary ancient
forests would store more carbon than
really any other ecosystems on the
entire planet and therefore probably
have the greatest cognitive capacity
more cells firing
with all of that living active matter
and and so I grew up with this paradox
of these magnificent ecosystems
beautiful fjords mountains you know Briz
Lee's you know right across the Georgia
Strait
I felt that so profoundly and then when
we went on family trips we'd go past
these massive you know lunar scale clear
cuts and I just had this sense how can
we be extracting so much and in my youth
I saw the forest depleted I saw this
massive pulp mill that was the lifeline
of my town actually shut down
deconstructed and literally shipped off
to China because too many trees had been
cut the industry couldn't be sustained
the fish you know salmon halibut caught
I mean fished out the mines
you know actually worked out within a
few decades and so like when I go back
to my hometown it's just it's
unrecognizable everything has been
extracted a lot of it is is regenerating
and bouncing back but it just led me on
the path and you're growing up at sort
of the edge of this massive extractive
economy even even in Canada even in
British Columbia growing up I just had
this sense I wanted to connect with the
patterns of life with living systems the
dynamics of nature and that led me to
this nascent field of complex living
systems and it was incredibly exciting
time I made my way to Berkeley for my
PhD and it was at a time when chaos
theory was just being developed by Steve
snail right down the hall you know
strange attractors fractal geometry
nonlinear dynamics and really in an
interdisciplinary way so in Berkeley you
know I was connecting you know the the
deep mathematics around this to
practical physics chemistry biology
economics sociology cross-cutting you
know what could be is in mathematics no
yes yes so I did my my doctorate at
Berkeley in applied mathematics but
really my focus was in ecological
economics which was just emerging at
that
extraordinary man Richard nor guard
really is the co-founder of the entire
field of ecological economics alongside
Robert Costanza and newer guard
continues to emphasize a deep
qualitative systems approach which kind
of complements where the hard edge
analytic side of ecological economics is
gone and pricing nature which maybe as
in this step you know and it's
fascinating I mean as I rewind and think
about early 90s leading up to the Rio
summit thinking about the contested
foundations of ecological economics a
lot of what we're still trying to work
through was right there you know with
someone like more guard emphasizing
profound questioning of worldviews
epistemologies really trying to reinvent
economics at a deep deep ground and then
Costanza making really important
technical contributions that could
immediately help us shift markets but
maybe have some unintended consequences
so just briefly let me let me go into
the briefly because it's such an
important bit because it is actually
what you sort of turning the the
contrast upon is how back then this
dilemma that we're in of on the one hand
yeah we need quantitative information in
mathematics is super useful into that
kind of analytical way of seeing is
enormously powerful but but how so often
we then and because it also slots into
the systems we've built and and is more
action oriented in them we dismiss the
qualitative aspects and and and the
patterns and the stuff that you like
please continue that you see me well
well exactly you know the the ways of
being you know cognition at a very deep
level our social matrix these deep deep
foundations of what it means to be human
so I emerged from graduate school in
1992 literally just as the Rio summit
was happening and was on a path to say
could we take
this nascent field of ecological
economics this nascent field of complex
living systems could we apply it in the
world what would that mean ecologists
even then we're saying and I Neve
noticed this too of Daniel ecologist
were saying the ecosystems we love are
falling apart how can I be a neutral
scientist in every field anthropologists
we're realizing these cultures I'm
studying from the outside are under such
attack from a certain Western
epistemology they can't survive I need
to become an activist anthropologist and
so in in field after field that there
was that ferment at Berkeley you know
around the world in the early 90s saying
we need new new ways of being new ways
of honoring each other's world's a world
that holds many worlds and so from the
early 90s have been trying to understand
you know this cognitive diversity that
is it's so powerful allistic diversity
cultural diversity you map that against
biological diversity
it's a beautiful correlation it is
highest at the equator and then moves
very smoothly as you head to the north
pole or to the South Pole decrease in by
our cultural diversity we don't fully
understand why but we do know there's
this profound correlation wherever
there's the the plant diversity the
ecological diversity there's greater
linguistic cultural diversity if that's
the true wealth of the planet which I
would argue and we could say if we go
back 12,000 years that's probably when
it peaked when we had the greatest by
our cultural diversity the greatest deep
adaptation of human cultures and
ecosystems and the greatest flourishing
of languages and and local autonomous
systems we you know we kind of have been
through these ages of empire and and
sort of these cognitive empires these
ways of ordering and structuring
knowledge and communication so from from
the beginning I've been thinking about
this deep weave of how can we have these
living systems emerge gracefully in a
profoundly place-based way
and that led me to write a book called
ecological design with the extraordinary
man sim van Duren who is a professor at
Berkeley so I kind of got to do a second
PhD it was just lovely I got to spend
another three years doing this deep dive
with sim exploring a living systems
perspective for the built environment
for landscapes for products
infrastructure what would that deep
weave look was it was that under a
research fellowship at Berkeley no you
know actually it was supported by Simms
nonprofit which was known as the
farallon's Institute in those days
so we literally got modest grant support
to do this research project and it was a
serious you know long-term collaboration
it's really really extraordinary and in
those days I was working closely with
Christopher Alexander as well who is a
legendary architect planner spent
decades at Berkeley and wrote these you
know beautiful books pattern language in
the nature of order which is yeah you've
helped him curate those not like how did
them that work like how did you work
together well yeah yeah the nature of
order
everyone must read it's it's four
volumes it's 1500 pages everybody who
can take a sabbatical level of the year
with it so so Chris was really looking
at the foundations of the living world
and he called it the structure of
wholeness then how do you actually look
at these deep relationships the flows of
water plants the trees the people every
part of the built environment every
piece of furniture in a nested scale
linking way from how do you think about
the design of a room to the house to the
street that it's on to the open spaces
to urban design to regional planet
regional planning and now we probably
extend it right to biosphere design but
Chris was trained as a mathematician
like me and we both have wandered very
para pathetically across many feel
and so Chris always kept his deep deep
mathematical training and he was looking
for deep structure deep pattern in the
built environment and very much in
ecological systems as well and he chris
is a wonderful / Majin so chris would
say well sustainability wonderful but so
much of it is just so ugly and lifeless
and and at the first day I was like what
are you talking about Chris I mean the
world's falling apart I mean we got to
just get things done technically - but
he had some deep deep points about how a
response to the sustainability crisis
needs to be deeply adapted deeply
attuned to place tuned to the ecology it
should be beautiful it should make us
feel whole and if we're on that path if
we're creating that kind of beauty
together then there's probably a way
that we can connect it to the
regeneration of different different
scales from neighborhoods to bioregions
to the planet would you how would you
see the impact of Chris's work Legon on
the one hand him I mean a pattern
languages is one of the the classics
that almost any architectural student
will at least pretend that they've read
or buy and have on their shelf but I'm
just wondering how many people actually
really taking deep enough of a dive into
this this opus that is really quite
remarkable and to then understand it and
apply it I mean I know there's a lot of
people who picked up on or we're
developing a pattern language for
evolutionary work in human societies and
lots of people work on pattern languages
and so that means definitely travel but
a particularly I found it that the depth
of work in the nature of order which I
only got through the first book always
thinking I can't wait to read the animal
3 but I'm still thinking that and and
how do you see it being has it
percolated through as it has reached
people that actually put it into
application well one of the fascinating
things is this work has influenced many
many different fields Daniel's so
software modern software the
object-oriented program
languages which is kind of the more
modern you know generation of
programming languages starting with C++
moving on to Java really the
architecture of the world now right the
coders all use this way of coding
because it allows software to become
this mycelial network of intersecting
intercommunicating programs and the core
people that developed those modern
languages were hugely influenced by
chris's work more you know from the
pattern language major of orden order
hadn't appeared yet but they literally
were looking at the beauty and elegance
of a pattern based way to perceive to
order knowledge to have communication
across teams and communities they
realized you could apply that to code
and they sort of had this hypothesis
elegant code is gonna have deep deep
patterns if you're constantly you know
trying to fix the latest bug and it's
occlude and you're building layer after
layer of just these ridiculous fixes
it's very brittle and they realized if
you take the time to go incredibly
deeply into the underlying patterns of
the code you can create elegance and you
can actually trade software that that
can inter communicate and evolve over
decades so those you know those early
programmers literally would sit around
reading Chris's work studying it
together my old neighbor in Berkeley
Ward Cunningham it's just extraordinary
visionary Ward developed what's now
known as agile programming which has
become agile in the water sense of agile
management you know not needing to have
years and years of planning but actually
adapting continuously as you're
developing software or running a project
so Ward deeply studied Chris's work use
that to develop what's become the wiki
he created the very first wiki literally
like the first page that any user could
update as a way to play with matters in
software and very quickly that became
Wikipedia Wow okay
and in in the kind of more built
environment planning and sustainability
field
do you see as being kind of direct
disciples or people who have really
drawn from Chris's work you know that's
a great question
chris is a towering figure in
architecture on a theoretical level but
when you try to apply his methods which
include deep deep participation it
removes that barrier between you know
you've got the architect here and the
clients here and they don't really
interact beyond the client saying a few
things Chris turns it into a profoundly
participatory process and something that
can can be done with entire communities
as they redesign neighborhoods doing
that in practice has challenged the
profession it's it's been hard to
contract around and so forth so I would
love to see profound explorations of
Chris's notions of structure of
wholeness and living systems and figure
out architectural practice around that
but it's tricky I'm wondering like
whether you can help me think through
something that have not done the the
research on but I may be you know from
from knowing Chris well I have a sense
that there's a connection between David
Siemens work on which is a kind of
phenomenological approach to
architecture and and Christopher's work
and I believe I mean I know that David
Seaman spend a lot of time at JG
Bennett's lab and one of the places that
also have influenced the regenerative
community and also there's international
futures forum like Tony Horton and the
three horizons and and the world systems
model all come somehow influenced from
from these early days at home Springs
and I know that certainly all the work
that they did seaman has done it is also
influenced by that and what where
recently a couple of years ago Rob
Hopkins unearthed from transition towns
he unearthed and an old paper of
Christopher Alexander's which is called
Christopher Alexander's challenge to
permaculture we're relatively early on
he was calling up the
the kind of permaculture layer approach
of canapes owns and and and can
basically a design approach that is
trying to create this integrative
self-sustaining permaculture whole of a
farm or a landscape through additive
processes and through processes that
Megan and Henry both office another calm
Springs person terms talking about
counterfeit holes rather than the
authentic holes and holes that are built
up of parts and the whole rather than in
a more regenerative way an unveiling the
whole that is their primary and the
potential of the whole to manifest by
really working from home as first rather
than creating wholeness by putting all
the perfect design pieces into place and
do you know how close the link between
like is there a link with Christopher
Alexander and and chrome Springs and and
that whole lineage a light one certainly
um I think I think somewhat
independently Chris develops very
profound ideas and methods around what
he called the field of homeless mm-hm
so experiential methods to actually
sense into what part of an ancient
carpet for instance has you know this
deep deep wholeness and how that
connects to other holes and like
networks of holes but as you're saying
Daniel verses counterfeit holes I mean
looking at hole ons looking at nested
systems of holes but looking at very
profound relationships not just being
contained within right so that's an
important way we think about nested
holes but holes actually interact in all
of these other rich ways you may sort of
leap up a few levels and connect over to
another hole over here and Chris wrote a
really important paper called a city is
not a tree
and what he meant by that is if you have
a tree like structure where you always
have to have a hierarchical hierarchical
way that you're integrating holes you'll
get some artificiality and that the real
organic life
a city like Jane Jacobs might have
celebrated actually involves more of a
lattice structure which is a much more
flexible way that you can have different
holes interconnecting and supporting
each other so he thought about this
incredibly profoundly you know in the
nature of order and what I love is its
it ultimately brings you back to
phenomenology it brings you back to the
lived experience of a place a room a
carpet Chris collected these extraordin
extraordinary is la mac-- rugs from
circa 10th to the 14th centuries he felt
that time period was that when the
greatest artistry and homeless was
created an evil quote wrote a whole book
about this called the foreshadowing of
21st century art and and you know
collected these amazing you know age
shit like you know they're they look
like they've got holes and the colors a
bit off and like they've been there for
centuries and yet you look at them and
they're beings you just sink into this
infinite interconnecting lattice and
it's a kind of a model of the entire
world's wholeness I think that and I'm
not sure but I'm putting ideas into
Chris's thinking there or whether my
sense is that it that's exactly where
the connection is its the dimension of
mind the participatory process of being
in relationship to other holes and yeah
it's not the the way that that and
contained within others so that so that
there is actually when you a need when
you contemplate the piece of art like
that it's there there's something in you
moving
um it's not just out there and yes and
that's precisely I think what what all
that larger school has in common and
paying attention to that that they
divide between mind and matter isn't
quite as either/or as current education
as us-trained it
well well exactly and another key link
is the work of David bone he was
thinking about
mechanics in this very profound way that
imbricated consciousness with the
weaving of the universe and developed
experiential techniques he called the
dialogue technique where you could have
people in a room kind of going down and
sensing kind of that emergent field
shared thoughts and it reminds me of
auto charmers beautiful work - it's
almost like an early precursor of what
Auto calls presencing elegant again it's
so beautiful the links you necklace
basically the link to boom is that henry
bought off who was also at chrome
Springs was one of Holmes PhD students
and and his whole like this work on the
difference between like that paper from
1971 on counterfeit and authentic holes
Otto's work when you when you read
presents the book that pre-canned that
the precursor of theory you he actually
deeply acknowledges that some of the
pennies that dropped in a conversation
with Henry bought off led him mounted to
this new path that he then developed so
beautifully so I find it really
fascinating the way that that is
actually a deep um sort of lineage in
multiple ways that that all dance around
this participatory ask yet of being in
Hope bringing forth a world like in
Madonna and marilla's terms yes yes well
much runnin Andrea you know with the the
beautiful beautiful auto police's theory
that we still haven't really understood
or deeply incorporated within you know
Western science it's it's beautiful and
it's important to understand it emerged
from South America it emerged in Chile
in a very distinct intellectual context
a global South context an alternative
epistemology and also and of course the
the Chilean Renaissance was
extraordinary brief window when you had
these amazing you know rich thinkers
actually you know getting government
ministry
to run and so forth but Otto poiesis is
it's so important to me I even named my
company out of polices and everyone said
you know don't do that no one can spell
it no one can say it no one knows what
it means but we have but we had to
because it to me it's the core inquiry
and so if we begin to weave this a
little bit towards the work that I'm
doing now Otto police's self-organizing
living systems and that sense of a
bounded being that cellular membrane is
so important in creating the context for
that living being and then the cells
within the cells making up a body that
also has its own autopoietic skin
membrane encircling it if we think about
regeneration the the core way that I
think it occurs in the world is what
much Ron Andrea called structural
coupling where literally you'd have two
and several systems interacting kind of
membrane two membrane in this profound
direct way and that if you can attend to
those flows and interactions which
create various sorts of patterns and
habits in a sense ultimately of
nurturing and love that if we attend to
those at the scale of our household and
then working our way out to our
neighborhoods and immediate communities
out to the the bio region that we might
really love and fall in love with
identify with connect with them whether
it's the mountain range right that holds
us or the river or in your case you have
this extraordinary Mediterranean Sea
lapping at the beach you know half a
mile away it's that those places are
just the weaving of these structural
couplings these with the deep interlock
but all of these beings as they connect
and much Ronna in his 90s is still
vibrant and still developing this work
and a few years ago he wrote a new book
really arguing that the basis of
cognition is love if they have to 50
years it's 60 years of trying to
understand autopoietic living systems he
realized what what is forged in the
earliest relationship between a baby and
the mother the father young organisms of
all species and even broader processes
not just living in the narrow biological
sense but if we think about the living
processes of the universe that really
that love and connection maybe is the
core that all and so what what does
regeneration means we're attending to
that in every cell of our body at every
scale and we can empirically you know
look at and experience this and of
course we can develop all kinds of
sophisticated you know models and
dashboards and and you know begin to
abstract from that and say is our bio
region you know within its fair share of
planetary boundary conditions and so
forth so we need all of those things as
well but I'd like to remind us that that
that deep experience of your own body as
a regenerative system in every moment
all of those around you all of your
different human communities and then the
places that you inhabit and all of their
beings you know my my neighbor
David Abram here in Santa Fe is just up
the hill he's been a dear friend for
many many years and David wrote this
beautiful book called the spell of the
sensuous and again back to phenomenology
you know David kind of unearthed the the
20th century deep thinking of people
like merleau-ponty about deep experience
at what how do we experience life and
and wove that all together and taught us
that we're really part of this weaving
with the more than human world you know
it's it's more than human it's we
couldn't imagine ourselves without these
failed wheels with that without these
allies and we cannot regenerate the
world as one species it's it's restoring
the flow
and the energy and the lines of
communication with all of these other
species their habitats their ecosystems
they can regenerate they can bounce back
and we can't possibly Stewart and
control all of this it's like we it's
just calling back our allies including
you know the mountains on the rivers and
all of these other species and I what
you've just said touches on so many
aspects of like I'm one of my I've only
done a few roles of being a second PhD
supervisor on a couple of PhDs and one
of them is a guy called Gonzalo Salazar
who's was a Chilean who there is PhD at
the same Institute where I did mine and
with Seton Baxter and he actually built
his entire PhD work on drawing from
Atanas work and basically expression we
like using this idea that we bring forth
the world in conversation which links to
the whole kind of living the questions
together that runs through my work and
yes and and we bring it forth through
love like weaving in both matter honors
biology of love but also the the notion
of biophilia that has been around for
quite a while but but then II Wilson has
kind of popularized and and for me that
this like mentioning David Abraham I
think David Abrams book is just so
beautiful there as well of the sensuous
and in this there's one paragraph way
way says that our senses and who we are
have been shaped in conviviality with
all other living beings like our ears
have been attuned to the howling of the
wolves in the food of the owls our eyes
have been sharpened by the deer running
in leather I can't remember the exact
quote but it's it's just pure poetry and
it speaks to exactly that larger
conversation of how like for me and
people get a little bit touchy when
overeducated privileged white guys like
me talk about the importance of
indigenous knowledge um but but I do
feel that the that is part of the
problem of now coming to a true healing
if we don't allow so-called
non-indigenous people were all
indigenous to Planet Earth and I think
that to ultimately whether we call it
rien habitation like the early bio
regionalists that or we call it
re-envision ization becoming native to
place again even if we weren't born
there but by by having these larger
conversations I think that's at the
heart of what we're trying to do with
our work in regeneration it's it's it's
about those how do we connect to place
how do we connect to region and to
planet but in a way that supports and
maintains the whole community of life at
all those scales so make that how did
you make that journey so from working
with Christopher you then set up your
company or two places and work for 10-15
years and that and then that's when you
ended up getting hit hunted by the
Capitol Institute well there there was
another really important step along the
way which is a wonderful nonprofit
conservation organization called eco
trust and they're based in what they
call salmon nation which I love it's
really the places the salmon can swim to
on the west coast of North America the
Pacific coast and it's a vast vast
region my home region right right in the
heart of salmon territory and so
Ecotrust even back in the early 2000s
when I spent three years there was
exploring what they called a
conservation economy so kind of an
interesting precursor maybe twin to a
regenerative economy and we were
literally exploring modern languages for
bioregional regeneration and how that
could roll up to create a conservation
economy and wonderful thing about
Ecotrust it's
they are continuing their still thriving
25 years later they're still
experimenting on the ground with things
like ecological forestry investment
funds so we helped connect one of those
early funds with federal level resources
in the early 2000 so very practically
saying could you take a little bit of
what we just discussed Daniel I mean
there's no way to to bring the depth of
that field of wholeness and the depth of
those relationships of structural
coupling and sensing place those are
fundamentally indigenous ways of knowing
and being there's no way to bring that
into an abstract financial transaction
that's the key conundrum right but even
back in the early 2000s he could trust
was wrestling they had incredible
ecologists on staff actually a very
strong program in indigenous knowledge
to their credit that's it's always been
core freaka trust to draw on the wisdom
of that in that region in that region
those were very strong as what sport
area and still vibrant cultures the
Haida
the Tlingit the quad youth where I grew
up and so they were trying to bridge
things like indigenous knowledge with
modern forest management and somehow
bring that into an investment term sheet
that says you'll somehow get some
returns tied to the health of the land
and not just to the extraction from the
land and they continue you know with
that inquiry so you know the bridge for
me was working with people like Chris
and sim testing ideas around what we now
call regenerative design we called a
ecological design it's just it's all the
same the same weaving working with those
ideas she's trying to shift into
practically getting things built on the
ground or practically shifting from
awful you know industrial forestry in
the Pacific Northwest to this day you
know you're clear cutting every 40 years
or so and just
leaving this devastated landscape
because it seems to optimize you know
the most extractive yeah you know
version you know of the economic model
where you've externalized everything you
know that the ravaged communities
destroyed ecosystems just if you can
ignore that and you run the number so it
looks like you cut it every forty years
or so you know we were trying to say
what if you have a whole range of values
and you're perceiving and understanding
connectivity you know between all of
these different parties so that maybe
there's a nearby municipality that
benefits from much better water quality
and quantity could they you know be a
part of this so all those explorations
it whether it's the built environment
you know working a lot with green
buildings and saying okay can we make it
even more energy-efficient less toxic
more joyful and abundant for the people
within it does that pencil and so I got
really obsessed in the early 2000s with
you know why deep living management of
ecosystems you know that could be
informed by traditional ecological
knowledge indigenous ways of knowing or
building you know in a way that would
allow us to be whole and and to preserve
all the broader systems around us that
you're not manufacturing anything toxic
because it's harm to workers and
ecosystems that you then bring into the
building but causes harm to the
occupants that you then dispose of that
causes farm somewhere else why did that
why did that seem to pencil the toxicity
the ridiculous energy is right or on the
land side you know why did it seem to
make sense to clear-cut or tortured you
industrial agriculture and that led me
you know to the next inquiry to well
clearly finance and economics are
completely disconnected from life from
from living systems from our lived
experience we have to reinvent it and so
with our company auto police's we
explored you know regenerative ownership
models financing models regenerative
design
really kind of bringing that weave back
together and it was you know messy and
complicated you know again and again we
would literally hit you know divergent
worldviews finally just so deep you know
where you're just rushing to to get the
final financing how do you talk to a
loan officer that Otto believes us about
living systems they they they're happy
to talk to you about the other benefits
ecologically and socially but at the end
of the day they just cannot see beyond
what they've been taught and what they
just feel so deeply is the essence of
the project which is this line of
numbers and so we played with you know
could you create the the economic
performance that included ecological and
social value layers and so that you know
without a polices we teamed up with our
shared colleague Jason twill who's now
based in Australia we launched this
project called the economics of change
to really work with real estate
investors all kinds of different actors
in that system to say could we open a
space to layer on economic value social
ecological value and and begin to
quantify it and again it's a it's a deep
epistemological mistake to think you
could take our lived experience or
ecological thriving and somehow turn it
into a series of numbers but we played
with that we tried to find ways to
communicate you know the the extreme
integrated set of benefits from a
regenerative building project and you
know did that work for several years and
again these deep deep worldview
conflicts where individuals at you know
GE Capital and different real estate
firms would totally understand it we
could talk as individuals they of course
I just went out fishing and I get it I
love it you know if we could incorporate
ecosystem values we get better buildings
and yet they couldn't single-handedly
move their company yeah I mean it's
funny that you brought up Jason because
as you were speaking before you
mentioned him I was thinking how it was
parallel between what you were
describing in what he was recalling of
his work of trying to transform the big
players in the build environment in the
stream back Olympus and also like my
conversation would with Bill Reid and
how very often when when Regenesis gets
hired for a job and there's that moment
where the client doesn't quite get it
what they are on about and because what
they're really looking is at the
finished designed development project
and the values that they can achieve by
selling it and in where's the the the
deeper deliverable of working in that
regenerative way is really the
capability of the entire system to self
manifest from each of the people in the
company but all the people they touch in
the community being lifted to being able
to manifest their potential through the
process of working in that way and and
and and it's just a complete shift one
of those kuhnian cubes were he looks all
very different but it's the same Cuban
and most companies still find it very
hard to make that shift it takes a while
for them to understand the deeper
significance yes and and the work of her
genital and profound you know to begin
to say could the unfolding of a building
a small development actually lead these
regenerative capacities being enhanced
in everybody touching the project in any
way and potentially even creating a
whole ecosystem of organizations and
that's the level I think where you can
actually begin to shift the kinds of
transactional models the investment the
ownership models when you start to have
a vibrant ecosystem many many different
organizations for profits nonprofits
academic institutions different levels
of government beginning to perceive with
a whole system's perspective beginning
to have this regenerative impulse and
this shared sense could we unfold this
potential together and and that that can
happen in a nested scales how did you
with John and make that move over to the
Capitol Institute then because I mean in
many ways that's that's the heart of
your work now but you're now working
with all these initiatives within the
regenerative communities Network where
people have come together saying yes we
can do this in the appropriate scale to
do this kind of work is at the bio
regional level its homed in on that work
yeah I've been thinking about this by
regional transformation process ever
since the control phase you know looking
really practically at sama nation right
so one very large beautiful by a
culturally diverse region and thinking
what you know what could we do to
systemically rewire the economy there in
build that sort of capacity and it was
early days and rough experiments and now
you know revisiting in the light of just
incredible work that's happened you know
for decades now and we you know starting
with sustainability moving to resilience
moving to regeneration it's all it's all
a huge weave and increasingly these
words these movements can become
something much deeper differentiated
still perhaps but working very
powerfully together with self-awareness
in a similar way to working with three
horizons gives you coherent ways to
think about different timescales and
strategies for action so if we think
about capital Institute's work in
regenerative economics they launched in
2010 I sort of found them very early
oddly what is this this is amazing
because almost no one was thinking about
regenerative economics or really
thinking about deep economic and
financial systems region design from the
perspective of living systems and so I
was following that work I met John
around 2013 we talked a lot we've done a
few projects together and then the time
was right in 2017 to say look could we
take the thought leadership work
John's pivotal 2015 paper on
regenerative capitalism some wonderful
storytelling work that had be done and
really say what would this mean on the
ground
right how could we and manage and design
a process for unfolding a regenerative
economy at a large landscape at a by a
regional scale what would that process
look like how can we nurture it how can
we feed it how can we support it and so
we we kind of drew on meg Wheatley's
wonderful work on on what she calls
emergent networks so this is very
different then oh yeah we you know there
are 10 or 15 well-defined projects and
we just set up a trade association and
it's a nice way to to communicate and
move things forward
this was a bit different because we
didn't really know of any buyer regions
on this path and so we kind of put up a
flare and said ok here's a here's a just
a light of is anybody interested in this
journey is anybody on this journey does
this even make sense and that's really
been the spirit it's when you when you
do an emergent network you try to give
it the loose as possible kind of
organizing integrity and in our case we
said look would you be interested in
kind of experimenting with say
principles of regenerative economics and
regeneration more broadly and we flew up
that flare and started to get some
enquiries you know ok this this is very
interesting you know some of us have
been thinking about this some
organizations are interested and so
forth and so we now have interest that
we can't possibly address there are just
dozens of by regions around the world
that would want to play and be connected
with it so for now Dania we have 15 by
regions on four continents a lot of
activity in Costa Rica Colombia Brazil
the United States and Canada
lovely project in the UK and South Devon
and then the park the idea is to learn
from each other
so bioregion to bioregion pure learning
to support this kind of regenerative
unfolding app by regional scale and that
starts with kind of some early energy a
strong enough team strong enough
capacity to say yes we can anchor this
long term so that could be a handful of
people in organizing
ideally from very diverse sectors
perspectives very deep and hopefully not
completely overlapping networks of
connection and then picture it like this
within a bio region you're trying to
grow a mycelium of regeneration a
mycelial a fungal root network of
regeneration so it's not about a
scorecard and sort of you're in you're
out I'll work with you or not it's like
wherever those hyphae wherever those
mycelial root tips right can connect and
say ah nutrients can flow here we may
not quite understand each other yet but
we're finding a way to work for
generatively where we can go deep and
begin to connect with each other's being
and connection and intention and not be
thrown off by words and frameworks and
just cognitive thinking actually dropped
down a few levels to really blob love of
what Otto Shermer would call presencing
you drop to that level and begin to
unfold prototypes and possibilities from
that deep level of shared field of
beginning to map and sense and and see
from a living systems perspective from a
full systems perspective so practically
in different regions in in the
regenerative communities network you've
got this weaving happen so you've got
all of these different organizations and
individuals beginning to connect
together find each other
launch initiatives in a very flexible
decentralized way and we feel that our
role is to support eight key dimensions
of regenerative infrastructure and these
have been kind of Co identified and
co-created with the network so again as
an emergent network we didn't quite know
what would be most helpful and what
we've sort of converged on for the
moment and this will continue to evolve
is kind of eight areas eight dimensions
that can support this mycelial growth so
education do they as well they don't map
against the eight qualities of
regenerative economics that correct
correct so the the eight principles give
us what we call a nice
calling them qualities in the last
conversation with John John is Swit
switching to calling them qualities as
well I like that I like that
Christopher Alexander actually played
with that and decided to use qualities
or in fact he called them properties
they identified 15 properties of
wholeness that are quite profound so yes
if we think about the v8 you know
qualities of a regenerative economy that
gives us kind of a North Star a purpose
for the work so we're trying to explore
together move towards achieving those
principles as interpreted by that
particular bio cultural context what I
love about those qualities is that
they're generative so I think John
really designed them in a way that would
enable deep inquiry open up you know the
right kinds of questions versus just
very cut and dried
you know more technical principles there
you look at you were just about to yes
and you named education which which
which one of the qualities of a
regenerative economists do you see
education match to so right so so the
qualities of a regenerative economy
include things like being in right
relationship or encouraging adaptation
and innovation or edge effect abundance
where you're kind of mycelium anaphoras
literally you've got one big mycelium
here another one over here what happens
when they begin to connect and you have
this unexpected nutrient flow between
them so that's kind of the overall
guiding purpose but then how do we do
the work and of course they're deep deep
qualities of being underneath all of
this and that's that's a whole other way
to think about the work but there are
eight dimensions of just practically
getting on with it and those include
your regenerative education so
everything from gene thinking about
regenerate world these do all kinds of
practical so those happen you actually
do agroforestry how do you create a food
forest garden right how do you do marine
or restoration and regeneration all of
those kinds of things transformative
leadership so how do you actually become
what we call a systems convener how do
you work in a by regional context or any
context in a way that unfolds potential
which creates a sense of possibility and
coherence so education leadership
narrative framing very important so
that's the third one
storytelling and capital Institute
actually did a lot of beautiful work
that was captured in what we call the
field guide to regenerative economy so
50 case studies of regenerative
enterprises from the US and in other
parts of the world so so storytelling
narrative you know being able to really
story this within a region to know you
know these these sort of sparks are
happening and connecting and doing
learning journeys around those the
fourth one is having a platform for
collaboration and communication and
we've experimented with one so a digital
platform that is called hive bright it's
fine
and there's a real deep art to actually
curating a digital community and we
haven't solved that as a network I'm
talking to many other people like David
Hudson and Steve Waddell with SDG
transformations form we're all kind of
wrestling with half math you digitally
hold this work I mean because because I
mean I signed up for that platform and
recently I reengaged with it and it just
felt like it hasn't really caught up
like to a point where there's a lot of
conversation going on like I was
surprised to having like felt bad that I
hadn't dropped in for maybe three months
and then I realized that not that much
and had actually been going on right now
I couldn't find it I know there's a
there's a fine art to you know on
boarding a digital community feeding it
curating having people engaged and it's
just not something we've been able to
put sufficient focus to so what's
happened is in the different bioregions
they're all evolving their own multiple
platforms and websites
you know whatsapp channels and on and on
and on and so it's cobbled together and
we don't have enough visibility right if
we had a shared platform that could
connect the work effectively it would
make all of the work visible and so
forth so we're in conversations with
other networks just in the same place
every once we've got platform fatigue
right it just it's too hard to have one
more place to engage doodle digitally so
we're realizing we've gone back to
actually the soft networks in place are
by far the most important the people
that are you know consciously meeting
connecting doing things together in
person walking the land together doing a
learning journey you know launching long
term collaborative that nothing can
replace that level of communication and
collaboration so then to kind of
complete you know those eight layers so
all of that is kind of sensing into the
system and and supporting some of the
key capacities to to do the work then
you need real ways to do systems mapping
to really understand geospatially right
the layers the water layers and energy
metabolic flows of materials associate
economic layers but then more
importantly causal system dynamics so
really using something like Kumu to do
deep systems mapping around power
relations causality within the region
but then other layers so our colleague
Glenn Page is doing amazing work on what
he calls transformation system analysis
and map it so literally try and
understand those key notable
intervention points leverage points in
the system and developing the fine art
of actually mapping and communicating
that together and it's an emerging field
and in hosting a working group around
transformation system analysis because
no one no one quite can do it yet in
practice we've got some tantalizing
clues I need to get in touch with them
because I would love for him to run
that fledging process against the ten
years of work and the network that I've
established here on New Yorker and and
to see whether it would give any
insights on how to particularly now that
the tourism is dead in the water
and after the pandemic there's there's
now compared to when when you came in
visited here and like the whole
positioning that I was doing of trying
to convince tourism to be the economic
engine of paying for the re
regionalization and the whole
regenerative process at the the island
scale is now not really an option
anymore and so it's gonna be interesting
yeah yeah so yeah exactly so so that
systems mapping flows very naturally
into design and planning at by original
scale which I know you've been deeply
involved with worked on guy education
courses around it's an emerging
discipline taking regenerative design
approaches things Regenesis group has
pioneered with storage place but than
many other practitioners and fields
there is a very profound field of
regional planning pioneered by Ian
McHarg
and and so kind of weaving together some
very deep thinking from Landscape
Architecture regional planning but then
saying it's not just the land planting
right it's deeply understanding the
economic transformation the social and
cultural factors and as you would say
it's really how do we design a
regenerative culture for that bio region
and of course in the completely
collaborative way and then in a way it
isn't just cultures on the side the it
is enacting regenerative culture it is
enacting a regenerative bio region which
means you've got to reground rewire all
the economic activity and you rewiring
the built environments you're rewiring
social relations and so forth and
finding this adaptive deep fit over time
but in many cases relies on traditional
ecological knowledge traditional ways of
knowing so the cycle then gets very
practical
mapping just signing and planning
evaluating and the network has adopted a
very beautiful approach called Blue
Marble evaluation which was developed by
Michael Quinn Patton who is a global
leader in this sort of field of how do
you know how do you evaluate and assess
projects of all types and it's called
Blue Marble because you have that image
of the earth you know floating in space
so your evaluation is literally is this
going to be transformative at different
scales in a way that will help us shift
to a thriving gyein system finally it
was one of the last books to arrive
before the started and so so we're
really kind of a test case within the
RCM for Blue Marble to really look at a
by regional scale where you have this
rich complexity so if you're trying to
assess how well you're doing in terms of
governance and what they call the
mailing conditions for long terms
sustained regenerative process you can
actually assess that qualitatively and
you can even get to some very simple
quantitative metrics when that's helpful
but from this sense not of so any
surface thing like oh yeah our water
quality was slightly better in this you
know sub hydrological basin you know or
co2 slightly better in this building
those are important but this is deep do
we have long-term conditions that will
enable the learning the transformation
to occur and so we're just testing us
now we're just kind of co-creating with
different bioregions
how would you do a baseline write to say
here's where we are on the
transformational process as we start in
a place like my Orca here are things
that we can tell immediately will be
weaknesses as we begin our
transformational process will
immediately begin to address those will
build deeper and deeper information
flows collaboration
processes ways of understanding together
how to continuously adapt our work and
then it connects of course to capital so
at the end of the day if we're gonna
rewire these by regional economies so
that literally they are regenerative
economy so that the flows the ownership
patterns to the the inclusivity the
ability to participate really
regenerative then we've got a shift the
investment within the by region and we
need to decarbonize we need to
regenerate land we need to create
systemic ways to include people in in
economic participation flows they can
disperse to the very edges and
distribute out throughout the bio region
rather than being highly centralized
typically in powerful urban centers how
do we have prosperity one of the
dilemmas that I see or the the real
challenges that that that entails is
that in order to reanalyze
a very generalized thriving regenerative
economy at the bio regional scale and
you need to do things that now in the
context of the pandemic that were in the
middle of em a beginning to make a lot
more sense to a lot more people because
we're now seeing how brittle our global
supply chains produce on demand kind of
supply chains of vast distances with
enormous externalized social and
environmental costs are breaking down
everywhere and so the argument for
regionalization and economic
diversification at the local and
regional scale in order to put people
back into employment after so many
systems are collapsing around us now
it's going to be easier to some extent
but em as we look into how to meet human
needs within not just meet them within
the copper tuna tees and constraints of
a given ecosystem bioregion em but
increase food water energy
self-sufficiency in Wawa or let's call
it self-reliance or sovereignty and not
not a kind of cutting off from the world
they're still betrayed em and to do so
in such a way that it actually also fits
with the ecosystems restoration agenda
and the drawdown agenda and the healing
of soils in the healing of waterways and
the read like the bringing back of
forests and the rewilding of land but
still producing food rather than
somewhere on the other side of the globe
with near slave labor and then have it
imported locally they they they are
quite a lot of really tight ropes to
work on and in order to for example if
I'm thinking of it as I so often do with
the island of Majorca where I live em on
the one hand we need to bring back many
more trees and like we're currently
working on a project called Bali iris
Wears Prada and a million trees in
influence all around the island but we
also need to that's why they need to be
food forests we need we need to somehow
produce more food for the local
population as we have done so far so
yeah it's it's a it's a complex
refitting of the human presence back
into ecosystems as as regenerative
presences well known degenerative
presences yes exactly and and we need to
attend to the current state which is
this incredibly complex evolutionary
process that has involved I do
harnessing the power of thermodynamics
so that the power of coal you know early
in the 19th century with large-scale
industrialization and all the different
path lights to our current you know
digital economy all of this has been
contingent all of it has deep
fascinating story dick eyes very very
tragic stories of various empires that
have caused problems in different areas
all of this needs to be woven together
and we need we need to look squarely at
the kind of the complex wicked mess that
the world is in and get to work
unraveling that and regenerating it so
we have to understand how capital is
held now and create viable models for a
just transition so that we shift we may
have a right of complementary currencies
Commons backed currencies we may have
very different kinds of economic
investment vehicles we may have rich
ways that were connecting together
financial capital social capital
ecological capital we haven't quite
solved that we yet but this is that just
saw its ended up there but because it
brings back to what we were talking
about the very beginning and I see a
huge amount of very well-meaning people
working with these frames of financial
capital economic ecological capital
social capital and they're a whole bunch
of nuances of naming a few others and on
the one hand I know that the people that
I know in this world are trying to use
these terms so we can actually create
the framework that allows the
internalization of externalities to
internalize in our balance sheet all the
socio-ecological effects of em bad
household management bad economics and
an extractive economy the danger and
where I feel like how do we safeguard
ourselves against that the minute we
create this multi capital system
the temptation to create that formula
that converts all on inhabitants to
economic capital is so high-end and it
will actually be asked for it will be
required for the but from the investor
types because they can only think in
that one unit and the minute we do that
that whole group I'm saying we like all
of us trying to do this work in service
to life and in service to the continued
evolution of life on this planet might
find ourselves suddenly see that work
that we built with the best of
intentions be co-opted for the largest
form of enclosure ever known in human
history that all other enclosure of the
Commons moves would be tiny in against
because the minute we have the vehicle
to quantify in financial terms human
relationships and the value of
ecosystems then yeah we've we've brought
it all into the market know exactly and
so it's a weaving of multiple forms of
capital not an inter convertibility so
it's understanding their their essence
how unique ways in different in
different parts of the world and not
allowing a dream roadway to to or
purchase natural capital but to Simpa
but as an begin to understand you know
in a holistic unified way how could net
flow properly engage and support all of
that so let me let me back up the
Capitals are incredibly awkward
incomplete approximations of what
actually is an under French rule fide
process of life we on this planet this
unified Gaia biosphere it is one
integral being with processes the the
trade the life for all of us that
nourishes all of us so maybe we need to
back all the way up to saying we need to
support an economic system that's
conducive to life and we've allowed
economic flows to distort and and hurt
and even kill living processes on this
planet we can redesign them but there
will be a transition that's necessary to
understand the deep structure of capital
patterns because that's the way economic
flows have been constructed we need to
map out how those flows can shift so
that that system actually ends up being
conducive to life to talk about a
unified way of supporting the
regeneration of every single watershed
on this planet that's that's what we
talked about with regenerative economics
how do we support regeneration of every
watershed every continent on this planet
every ecosystem yeah and all humanity
and mission but I can't and after the
transition question right it we can
imagine fresh economic systems that I
that I think are conducive to life and
capital institute has really focused on
that and many others that the well-being
economy Alliance there's such a rich
diversity
I'm uncountable exciting dynamic visions
of where we could go but there's so
little work on the deep gene question
how can we make a culturally palatable
narrative around how that transition
will work how can we run numbers from
this reductionist economy to this
holistic unified economy how do you even
translate we build bridges between them
and how do you map out you know
literally turning down the petrol
economy and everything like that
the petro extractive economy where
financial flows have largely been tied
to how much can you extract how quickly
that's just that's how they're designed
it's like not a great design drove all
kinds of interesting things it's it
can't go on like that so we need to
shift to shift the up the regenerative
economy and literally it Daniel what's
so simple as literally shifting from
you're rewarded for extracting and
destroying just because that's the
system's design no guilty design if I'm
a bright person and I can use these
flows in a certain way I can do well for
my family and extended community and I
forget that at the end of the day it's
tied to something destroying life
somewhere else on the other hand if we
if we can rebuild an economy where the
flows are based on how much are you
regenerating and relieving and
reconnecting restoring place by place
it's you're turning the extractive
you're bringing up the regenitive and
you've got to have a way to communicate
that story at a national level at a UN
level at a community level and I feel
like we're on the verge of building that
story so for instance I have a wonderful
colleague
working at a non-profit literally
mapping how do we turn off the oil
infrastructure systematically in an
optimal way over time it's how we're
building up the regenerative economy can
we can model that globally they're very
powerful software models to do that and
we can story that right we ought to
build a space a political space to story
that that removes the fear of well flee
you know without oil we're gonna we're
gonna starve all the food chains you
know will collapse and so forth but you
know we have to story it in a way that
we we can have a stable transition but
that's an incredibly deep technical
problem as well it's its most deeply
Trull and worldview problem of how to
even want and imagine our way into that
but technically it's really interesting
and deep and solvable to really map out
you know shutting down the petro turning
up 3 J and doing that maybe over 10
years hmm yeah no I mean I think that a
just before we wind up because we could
easily talk for another two hours the
two projects that that we've been
connecting on both the regenerative
platform as one experiment of how to em
both showcase connect to each other and
also connect to potential investors and
and and also philanthropic funders
regenerative projects around the world
and and then then the work with with the
British or the former British
Commonwealth now the the Commonwealth of
Nations and how do you see those two
initiatives what is now turning into the
Commonwealth alliance taking a critical
role in that and and also the enabling
structure that the regional rasa T
Network and that we've been working on
how do you see them fitting it into this
story yes yes well let me start with
rigidity it's part of this wonderful
ecosystem of transformative projects
around rejecting economics not just
funding specific regenerative projects
but literally regenerating finance
regenerating economics and decent
regenerating what that can mean so
Regeneron T is looking very practically
at connecting visionary projects that
applied to say the Buckminster Fuller
challenge giving them more visibility
telling their stories having a shared
digital platform to give to foundations
and even private investors that would be
aligned we're seeing all kinds of
experiments around you know software
platforms even just lose social
communities that can take you know a
rich diverse range of projects and
connect them to be kind of a second
example to show you that generosity is
happening and kind of this rich mix of
invention there's an a very important
initiative called once and landscapes
for 1 billion people it's in convened
once you know it by eco agriculture
partners UNDP World Wildlife fund's in a
landscape scale investment platform
where you have to very much like a bi
original operative the regenerative
communities Network a vibrant landscape
convening right on going way to get key
land owners and then representatives of
grassroots landowners get them to
have a sheared picture of their
landscape where it could go regenerative
Li and then present then ya present a
coherent portfolio projects to investors
one of the the key partners in that is
common land and I like what yes my work
here and basically I think that that's
actually the easiest way in my
particular case that here may or case if
I can position the for return strategy
and common land kind of work as a vision
for the redevelopment of the Balearic
economy across the four islands and then
using the link the existing link that
that common land has to ecosystems
restoration camp and that the spinning
out of
ecosystems restoration come in and John
Lou's work linking that with the already
existing proposal for this this baleares
where I think them then there might be
particularly in this new situation a a
platform where we can actually begin to
start it's really complicated local work
of enrolling all these different
perspectives people that have made a lot
of money in tourism for 50 years but
don't really have that the kind of
holistic worldview that would be a
wonderful precondition for having a
[Music]
better M synteny in this conversation
like initially it will be a clash of
worldviews it was there will be a lot of
co-learning to bridge languages and all
that in in and having lived for 10 years
the actual day-to-day complexity of
trying something as audacious of turning
an entire island economy around and we
had this conversation before I I
constantly find that there is attention
to the kind of global connecting and
global storytelling and how do we do
this in a global way globally applied
regionally applied but globally
collaborative in solidarity and
connected and through peer-to-peer
learning energizing the whole process
and it's that tension between each and
every one of us having to make a
decision of how much of our
energy spirit breath attention we give
to the cohesiveness of the network and
the co-learning and the the kind of
storytelling we can do together and then
because so much of the basic assumption
is that it has to come out of place it
has to be attuned to by a cultural
uniqueness so it it's it's this slight
almost contradiction that we're trying
to create patterns and processes but
we're deeply acknowledging that they
will be slightly different or completely
different in different contexts yes so
yeah how do you like because this must
be the case for every single member in
every single of the initiatives that you
that you're working with and like to put
it sort of simply in an example it's
like how many zoom calls do I have with
the arch the end with the return of
community network each months and how
many local em can avoid cafes and in
meetings with local government and local
activists groups and local business
owners do I have in local universities
in order to enlist more and more people
into the the regional Alliance um is
that Orion coming out a little bit with
with all yeah yeah no absolutely the
system's conveners in each of the by
regions that we're supporting are
extraordinary people they're busy we
have incredible demands on their time
and we're trying to provide shared
infrastructure that has real immediate
practical value things like blue marble
things like a shared regenerative
investment platform which we're also
working on you know within the RCM in
fact Mexico City is pioneering it's
fantastic thing SVX Mexico which is a
regenerative finance lab which will
become a fun soon to find projects
throughout Latin America those things
have tangible immediate value so we're
only interested in in giving the
bioregions practical things that they
can run with and what we ask in return
is the learning that the bioregions
learn from each other and that we tried
capture that we've got that back into
this entire network flow of learning but
you're absolutely right that the you
can't spend all of your time telling
your story to five different global
networks I mean the work is on the
ground that's what matters and if you're
getting really valuable tools and
processes from your alliance with
different networks and kind of local
initiatives great but those platforms of
those tools those processes have to be
deeply attuned to place and so you're
scaling across you're not taking some
rigid set of rules and applying it into
place you're you're taking a blue marble
that is just very deeply mapped 'iv to
place-based expression so let me just
tie that back to common earth as we wrap
up so common earth which you've been
instrumental in Daniel and many of our
colleagues common earth is quite
extraordinary you know it's a it's a an
effort to bring regenerative development
into the 54 nations of the Commonwealth
of Nations and this very courageous
small common earth nonprofit for three
or four years now has been convening at
the Commonwealth level bringing together
regenerative development practitioners
with key national representatives from
nations ready to move at least with the
pilot project at least some region you
know that that is connected to this so
something extraordinary is happening now
where the nations of the Commonwealth
are getting very excited about the
original thought to do a regenerative
roadmap at national scale so there's
leading testing at a regional scale
various regenerative processes
throughout the Commonwealth and that's
created enough excitement that now is
the time to say New Zealand be aiding a
regenerative roadmap it would be a
national approach to regeneration in its
full ecological economic dimensions
literally thinking about rewiring it
towards the regenerative economy litter
regenerating ecosystems literally
working on the weaving of human
communities so Maori communities would
be critically important in leading such
an initiative so all the way from yes
we're going to decarbonize when we draw
down type goals we can use draw down
type strategies on the carbon side but
then all these other things you know
completely rewiring the economy and
using this as a way to build
regenerative capacity so you're not
doing all of this just a technical level
you're doing it in that way which is
bringing people together in this
powerful for weaving and and
reconnecting them with their place could
such a thing be mapped out so we're
experimenting with this in Costa Rica so
emerging from the work of the
regenerative communities network edward
molar is leading an effort to talk about
you know what would a regenerative
roadmap look like for Costa Rica how
could that inform efforts in New Zealand
other parts of the Commonwealth we're
hearing you know kind of murmurings that
Iceland might do such a thing in
connection with what the well-being
economy Alliance so this is another
really interesting scale of regeneration
that's emerging I think Daniel where we
with the regenerative communities
network we've been really focused on bio
region and watershed tangible physical
you know delineated by mountains in
grasslands and things you can touch and
see
but nations tend to have somewhat
arbitrary boundaries however they have a
gravitas and energy they they are
typically what you what you go to the UN
with and engage in climate negotiations
and biodiversity negotiations with
there's no reason not to engage
regeneration at national scales no
particularly small nations so Zealand's
Iceland's Costa Rica's relatively small
countries in area and population seem to
be viable
they're almost like small groups of bio
regions that you really could imagine
yeah you could have every single bio
region in Costa Rica or New Zealand
vibrant and really bubbling up and and
doing powerful grassroots up work that
you then kind of roll up and say well
that becomes an integrated way we go up
and down scales from water
by Regent optimation and back down and
as we have a handful of these nations
saying yes we're charting out a very
deliberate regenerative pathway suddenly
you have another model at the UN level
having another way SDGs or rickles but
do so many other things as well whether
innocence since a broader convene that
first meeting that that common work
earth grew out of over the last why but
now it's four years and I really felt
sort of almost spellbound by the put
potential that that would lie and also
the potential of using what historically
is a strange Club that has been born out
of colonialism but but really turning
that historical trauma and grief around
and now really empowering like like the
story of New Zealand is just amazing
because it is so strongly carried by the
regenerative practitioners in New
Zealand just recently connected so that
somebody from a Maori tribe connected to
my work was wanted to bring it to her
tribe and she was just over the moon
to hear that there were all these Maori
elders already deeply steeped in
regenerative work and already having
explored how similar the the deeper
value in insights
xgr between that kind of Western develop
frame around regeneration and their own
indigenous cosmovision that they've been
carrying as a wisdom carrier for for
millennia and so it's really beautiful
that that works coming together but you
said feel like I always there was 53
Nations or has Costa Rica now joined the
Commonwealth because they're doing a
road map well actually it's very helpful
that Costa Rica is not part of the
Commonwealth because it can be a neutral
example
so rather than any sort of sentence of
competition or you know my my
regenerative roadmaps better than yours
having just a a neutral well respected
external country
country known for peace no standing army
known for having one of the highest
years of protected land for Costa Rica
you know to just gently set this example
and say this isn't fine no we're
learning alongside all of you it gives
the Commonwealth ironically kind of room
to maneuver and so we see this very rich
dialog just happening now between Costa
Rica and New Zealand thinking about
these regenerative roadmap really wants
to play you know their destination
within and outside the Commonwealth and
you know it just brings me to a very
simple definition of regeneration it's
just learning to be human
you know more than human world and the
traditional cultures ah you like that
traditional cultures have focused on the
incredibly exquisite challenging
sometimes painful task of being human in
community and knowing what that means in
terms of our relation to the to the
broader more than human world to the
other beings both biological and the
stone beings and the water peeing that I
just thought of it beautiful no this is
it's entirely aligned with um you know
the guy that I like there's a there's a
guy in Japan um called Christopher chase
who have been curating a couple of
Facebook pages with over the last few
years and we had a conversation in which
um similar like that just emerged out of
you this this this this idea of really
at the essence of it
life is a regenerative community that's
what like if we want to say how does
life create conditions to conducive to
life well life is not a bunch of
individuals fighting for survival life
is a planetary process that makes the
entire planet more apt for more life to
be more to generate more abundance what
adversity and keep integrating
diversity and abundance predominantly
through collaborative processes
competition is just sort of fine-tuning
around the edges they're the real
process of life is symbiosis and
integration through collaboration and
and in many ways learning to be human in
a more than human world is another way
of saying how do we fit into that more
than human community of life and how
will we fit into that pattern of
creating conditions conducive to life so
beautiful I love it a perfect place to
end I need to wrap this has been so
lovely and I just I just want to finish
with a couple of thoughts when we think
about my original regeneration we can
also engage even with large companies I
don't want to leave the impression that
this is strictly about real okha lysing
everything and here we might differ
slightly which is fine but if we engage
a large company we're saying that the
starting inquiry would be what would it
mean for all of your activities across
your office's your supply chain
your whole vendor ecosystem all of that
to be regenerative and that ultimately
will land you in all the different
bioregions and places where it has a
footprint so imagine a company on a
regenerative journey that actually works
in a way that we talked about they'll
read that might work recently where you
know you're trying to build regenerative
capacity through that process so imagine
a large company actually having all of
its employees begin to be under new
generative jury buddy they're touching
and connecting with all across their
whole footprint and such a company might
realize it might make a lot more sense
to be much more by regional and have you
know highly localized circular economy
processes you know much more place-based
forms of manufacturing but there might
still be some things irons not that
prevalent you know in most bio regions
it's probably a good idea to trade a bit
of iron rather
in extracting it in a way that's
destructive in a certain region so
instead of an economy of scale or you
know comparative advantage what if it's
about regenerative advantage you know
under the materials and processes happen
in certain ways to you know to minimize
any any negative impact and those
inspire regions don't have to even
address that so that's with you I mean
that basically the work that I did with
a cover yeah two thousand thirteen
fourteen fifteen using my York as a as
an example and they liked the beauty was
the tomtom and the long-range innovation
manager of ekkuva was entirely in in the
spirit of let's just try to do it in
order to learn from it not in order to
necessarily succeed and we were
basically asking the questions could we
use waste streams on majorca to produce
all the detergents and cleaning products
that hotel industry needs or may occur
using a multinational well-established
ecological detergent company like ekkuva
as a knowledge partner that would then
actually create and we did to some
extent just that little project despite
the fact that eventually it stopped
being funded and our process was
engaging the local chemical industry the
local bio innovation class that the
local tourism cluster and in a kind of
thinking about mapping the resource
flows on the island and experimenting
with what you can do with bio
fermentation of orange and all in the
orange peel law and that the the waste
products of olive presses and and what
while the project hasn't continued the
way of questioning we brought to the
island has landed we are these clusters
of businesses that are now asking those
questions and so it is actually still
living on and and that notion that we
had that it was on the one hand a
complete innovation in product design
based on its circular biomaterials
economy and how would we do that but
also an innovation in
business model design how a
multinational more as a knowledge
capacity holder can partner with
regional businesses to form these kind
of what control and would call
regenerative Enterprise ecologies that
that would actually help a flourishing
regional regenerative economies to
happen and where they were increasingly
the multinational becomes a network that
facilitates what it still needs to be
traded or needs to be exchanged whether
its ideas innovation and knowledge or
whether it's the core elements that you
can produce locally that's where where I
think a lot of the large corporates
could reinvent themselves into these
enabling networks of re regionalization
in my mind so I'm we're not at all like
because you said we might differ I don't
think all beautiful we we have we have
woven together that best strand
that's beautiful and I would also just
say the planet is to life these these
living systems this immense biological
diversity that we've asked
biogeochemical cycles hydrological
cycles the planet is still fundamentally
alive and we've learned that in many
ecosystems not all but in many that if
you simply remove some of the key
pressures make a few key interventions
maybe a few key plantings here and there
a few check day up erosion over there it
can come back so quickly you know within
you wouldn't over-read dolphins jumping
in the bay of life stop the pressure
bill read talks about eighteen months
you know as sort of a common baseline
but many ecosystems they won't be
restored but they can move from a
terrible kind of helix of degeneration
into moving towards being able to self
regenerate and and beyond that at that
adaptive spiral of increasing diversity
and rebuilding itself
but the planet knows how to do this at
that capacity there is still roughly 400
and indigenous people that actually are
suits for vastly the you know greater
share of biological diversity than the
net-net are and a very very large piece
of the planet so there's this kind of
green indigenous heart of the world that
is waiting for us to remove the
extractive infrastructure for our
messages where it's been pushed out to
and that green heart will move into the
rest of the world and that is happening
[Music]
sorry and you know and underneath all
this you know as we think about how do
we actually regenerate we have all of
this that's still vibrant one thriving
that we just need to connect to and
listen and support remove those key
pressures and so there's this mycelium
of regeneration the fungal root network
that is unstoppable I think it really
has reached that stage and it's weaving
together the different networks the NGOs
even businesses they're learning to
create ecosystems of transformation
right they're moving beyond you know
from from ego to eco as Otto Sharma
would say you know but moving to this
unbelievably rich network distributed
mycelial revolve life and those those
processes are happening the innovation
ring for instance in technical digital
systems there's now a thing called a do
a dho a digital decentralized hellenic
organization it's like a digital model
our life happens and so we could
literally switch on a regenerative set
of financial flows almost overnight in a
way that would actually mirror this and
IC allele interconnection but we can't
just do that we've gotta nurture the
soil we've got a nurture this the story
and the narratives and said that we're
all really excited to actually you know
turn off the petrol turn on turn up the
regenerative and do that in an
agreed-upon hopefully ten year or five
year I think ten year more realistic
time frame yeah we have let me come back
to that basically often people say how
can you be so audaciously positive and
about this this vision of diverse
regenerative cultures everywhere around
the world and really it's when you align
with life then you have the biggest ally
possible which is life itself and in an
in a circle and and yet there's so much
still to be learned from those who have
been stewarding the last pockets of of
healthy expression of life creating
conditions conducive to life that is
it's this beautiful synthesis not a
going back to some kind of over
idealized indigenous past but that's why
I like the word real digitization which
which we can't which which we kind of
waited coil infested white people need
the guidance of indigenous knowledge to
do this well but we we can re indigenous
all of us and and also so many of the
the indigenous indigenous nations have
also been transformed and co-opted and
and affected by the the insidious
development agenda and and industrial
growth society so they're not as pure
and imperfect as sometimes gets gets
printed trains so it's exactly Koller
knee and but but the ally is really life
itself like all of us as expression
exactly a world of many worlds a world
of men made different epistemologies
ontologies ways of being ways of seeing
they don't all have to be made
compatible and interconnect
they can be respectfully learning and
doing diplomacy
you know while having this this deep
differentiation of cultures and places
there's a beautiful called low-tech ello
- Tek in other words kind of traditional
ecological knowledge and it's about
traditional stewardship of landscapes in
20 different countries around the world
beautiful book by Julia Watson and so
she's a landscape architect at Harvard
leaders I'm sorry yes a month ago
okay so ordinary a woman I just met
Julia Watson Willie Watson sorry yeah
it's had a wonderful meeting work from
her base at both Harvard and Columbia
she's done field work for many many
years in 20 countries looking at vivid
current expressions of traditional ways
of seeing and working with the landscape
and these are adaptive they're not fixed
in time these have been continuously
evolving you know there's been learning
from neighboring cultures and
communities adaptations and so already
now including certain modern materials
and technologies but all from local
cultures still carrying you know deep
adaptation to place you know centuries
and millennia in cases of deep
co-creation with the landscape and she
argues as a landscape architect this is
cutting edge little the depth of that
way of knowing and working with
landscape is incomparable with a
technical intervention like you put in a
BIOS well here you know a retention pond
there it's it is it's so deep because
it's getting this question of being
human in a more than human world
wonderful thank you thank you so
wonderful conversation let me just stop
the recording here